[SPEAKER_01]: I was wondering if we could talk about anicca once again.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's been a while.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I found some suttas pointed out by another friend, which shows where the... how to develop or
[SPEAKER_01]: Where that perception of anicca should be developed, how it should be developed, what's the importance of it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there are these three things.
[SPEAKER_01]: The view of satisfaction, the view of self and wrong view.
[SPEAKER_01]: And these other three things are to be developed for abandoning those three things.
[SPEAKER_01]: The perception of impermanence,
[SPEAKER_01]: Anicca used to be developed for abandoning the view of satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the perception.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anicca used to be developed to abandon the view that things are satisfying.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, I have a view that this is satisfying my situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's great.
[SPEAKER_01]: I like, you know, my body is good.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's working.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm satisfied.
[SPEAKER_00]: My life, my family, my views, my convictions are satisfying to me.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that's why, like, when, as this other suttas say, like, you know, when samanas and brāhmaṇas live withdrawn from sensuality physically, but then they start falling into views, like, really start holding the views, because that becomes where they find their safety and satisfaction and comfort in their convictions.
[SPEAKER_00]: So,
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you could see, like, well, we said that before, I think, obviously, in many other talks.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anicca needs to be... can only be understood on that personal level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when you find things that are dear to you and contemplate their cessation or change, the feeling that you get as a result of it, well, that's the closest to anicca you can get in the beginning.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the direction to go.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the problem is, obviously, with like a, you know, contemporary Buddhism, the whole kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: Mass of commentaries and, like, scholarly interpretation of terminologies and so on, that's not paired with the fundamental practice and the right view, then you get these ideas of the scientific, that things are constantly changing and that's why they're not real and that's why dukkha is not real.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you realize, well, then the Buddha would have simply said that.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said everything is constantly changing and none of your pain is real and nothing is ever real.
[SPEAKER_00]: But he didn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: He said contemplate impermanence to overcome satisfaction, to abandon satisfaction in things, in dhammas, in views, in possessions.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you could realize anybody can adopt the view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Any scientist who is measuring, sort of physicist or whatever,
[SPEAKER_00]: That it's measuring data, measuring things, measuring electrons constantly moving, would say, oh, things are constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anybody can develop that view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anybody can adopt that view.
[SPEAKER_00]: No prerequisites needed.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just need to hear it and need to be pleased about it, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to endure anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to keep the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to... well, you don't need to abandon safety that you find in the world and all the satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just adopt the view.
[SPEAKER_00]: That everything is constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, often people like that, people that follow commentaries and and kind of contemporary interpretations, would often try and connect and say, yes, of course, modern science has proven that everything is constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, see, the Buddha also said that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the modern science has proven that the Buddha was right, as if such thing is possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Putujana can prove an arahant right.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just insane.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, so the whole the whole idea of, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Things constantly changing, and everything is constant flux, and it is linear.
[SPEAKER_00]: A leads to B, leads to C, leads to D, and that's how everything is going and moving, and one to the next, and that's why nothing is real, that's why nothing is permanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't require anything, nor would that view uproot your satisfaction in the world.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would not make a difference.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would just provide a new gloss, the latest veneer of kind of hindsight interpretation of what it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: But things can never be experienced like that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, if things are constantly changing, second to second, you would not be a self-conscious being.
[SPEAKER_00]: There would be no steadier reference point that's not changing as much.
[SPEAKER_00]: You would simply be swept from A to B and C and there would be no... there would not even be a notion of memory.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the whole point is... and see, like, again, when people adopt that view, although they might draw it from science or from whatever, commentary, explanation and so on, it's not... it does not remain just merely intellectual.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is the whole kind of emotional side invested in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because people would have arrived at the Buddha's teaching, because they want to be free from suffering, but then they jumped into this view, that then, as I said, retroactively describes what happens to you, which is why nothing is real, which is why you don't suffer, and then they get emotionally invested in that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they are suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yes.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, basically, they want to be free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So they want to be free from suffering, so they invest
[SPEAKER_00]: In this explanation that tells them that their suffering is not real, because everything is constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not going to be easy for them to then just drop that view, because that means now they have to drop their whole idea of practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Their whole idea of that kind of relief that they got from the belief that their suffering is not real.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that is necessary.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they were to actually start to understand the endurance... Because, you know, when the Buddha described, there is... there is arising is manifest, ceasing is manifest, and persisting while changing is manifest.
[SPEAKER_00]: The three characteristics.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, persisting while changing means exactly that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Persisting as the same thing while changing on a different level.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you realize everything, everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's like my intention to sit here and talk to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: It remains persisting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if I change my mind, I'll get up and walk out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, all these other things that are constantly changing, my arms are moving, my mouth is moving, I'm speaking, different sounds are coming out, different questions, different ideas, all of that is on a lower level.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that is changing, while my intention to remain seated, talking to you, is not changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you were to say, well, that intention
[SPEAKER_00]: To remain seated here and talk to you, well, that's just an idea.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just... Well, it is an idea.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's an image.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: And furthermore, if there is not idea in my mind to sit here and talk to you, none of these smaller things that I do would be intelligible.
[SPEAKER_00]: They would make no sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because there would be no unifying idea.
[SPEAKER_00]: There would be no idea that persists while these things within that idea are changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, a person, if they were to... if they were to basically overcome their scientific view of everything is in a constant flux and changing from A to B to C and nothing is real and it's just empty concepts, they... like, from where they're standing, when they hear the third characteristic that the Buddha talked about, persisting while remaining the same... sorry, changing while remaining the same or persisting while changing, depending on translation, that would, to them, feel like eternity, like that's permanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, but that's all, that's permanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, first you have to now adopt the idea that things are permanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: And see how that feels.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, start seeing, okay, but that permanence is not mine.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not for me.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not I am.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the closest, that's much closer to the impermanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: To actual anicca, the putujana can come.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not about denying things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about removing your satisfaction and sense of safety that's found in them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, ironically enough, the view that everything is constantly changing, moment to moment, flux, consciousness, just coming and going, coming and going, is obviously a thing that's not changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Their view is not changing on that level.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's basically where they find satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_00]: In that explanation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Of how things are, of what's happening to me, of why my suffering is not real, and if I stick to it, all the concepts will just disappear in my mind, and I would be left with a pure reality.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well, pure reality is just another concept you just used.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the concepts were never the problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's again what the Buddha said himself.
[SPEAKER_00]: As far as the language goes, as far as the words and designations go, that's how far Tathāgata has explained the dhamma.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no issue.
[SPEAKER_00]: There's no need to say our words are just mere concepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is a real reality which you just express through words, which is a mere concept, which means real reality is just mere concepts then as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you possibly perceive anything that would not involve a notion of a concept of it?
[SPEAKER_00]: And he said, as far as the designation goes, as far as nāmarūpa goes, as far as the words and language goes, the Tāgata has understood it and explained it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not less, not more than that.
[SPEAKER_00]: If somebody claims that there is more that they can explain, more than your language can convey, or less, they don't know what they're talking about.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not possible, he said.
[SPEAKER_00]: Such thing is not possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if somebody wants to contemplate anicca, exactly, find
[SPEAKER_00]: Things, experiences in your life, that you are finding satisfaction in, they're satisfying for you, that you find safety in, all of that, and see it real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no reason to deny it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is no reason to to to undermine it with these explanatory views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, but that's not real, because electrons are constantly moving and and collapse or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's real as such.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, you wouldn't be finding safety in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what's the problem then?
[SPEAKER_00]: The problem then is, when you reflexively recognize your situation, oh, I am finding safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say, like the typical example would be, I'm finding safety in my family.
[SPEAKER_00]: My family is my satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things I work for, things I produce, things I have.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is my satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, if you are honest and you recognize that your satisfaction rests upon these things that are fundamentally not in your control,
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you feel anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you feel the dread.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you feel, what if I lose these things?
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do I free from suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, you could go the route of, as I said, commentarial ideas.
[SPEAKER_00]: They had nothing to do with the early texts.
[SPEAKER_00]: They were introduced much later, of deny the reality of those things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Say, your son, your daughter, they're not real.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're just electrons and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: And hammer in that until you kind of deny any
[SPEAKER_00]: Dependence on it, while you're still dependent on it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because no amount of saying it's just electrons would make you not feel suffering if you were to lose them there and then.
[SPEAKER_00]: In hindsight, then, you would explain that that wasn't suffering, it was just this.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, first and foremost, you will feel it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, go the route that actually the Buddha said you should go, if you want to prove the suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Recognize that your satisfaction, your safety, depends upon those things that are not in your control.
[SPEAKER_00]: Allow that feeling to endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can mind endure that feeling of what if I lose everything that's dear to me?
[SPEAKER_00]: Through purification of virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, through sense restraint and virtue, your mind becomes stronger and is able to endure such anxious thoughts and possibilities.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, gets to see them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even the dearest of those things, the dearest of assumptions, the dearest of perceptions that I had, have, cannot be owned in and of itself.
[SPEAKER_00]: It is unownable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind doesn't move in face of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mind is not afraid from it anymore.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, what if...
[SPEAKER_00]: I better stop thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I better either explain that they're not real or distract myself from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: You remain with those things presently enduring for you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that pressure, those feelings, the anxiety, what if I lose things that I love, that remains there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the mind stops fighting them, stops trying to sort of deny them, or stops trying to look away.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you get to see, well, it has a reason on its own, even the notion of attachment.
[SPEAKER_00]: As such, it's not in my control.
[SPEAKER_00]: As such, it is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever has come to be,
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it's there, that is its impermanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Its manifestation is its unknown ability.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you didn't create things.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just find them presented to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then you get attached to everything else, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: But all that's secondary to their manifestation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So that's the Sotāpanna's understanding.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever is of the nature to manifest, it's because of that manifestation that it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because I will observe its ending.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's also another problem with that whole commentarial notion of things constantly in a flux of change.
[SPEAKER_00]: It means you need to observe things ending to know the impermanence.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that doesn't apply to any things of the personal matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you observe your life ending?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, if you want to understand the commentarial type of impermanence, you need to die.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you're still alive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your life is still here, enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not ending.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how can you then be free from the five aggregates and saṃsāra?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, by that view, the ending means you need to observe it gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: But that's impossible.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, quite the opposite, anicca does not require things to disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: It actually requires them to be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why the Sotāpanna's understanding is, whatever is of the nature to manifest,
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not whatever was on the nature to be here and it's now gone.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Whatever's here, because it's here, that's why it's unownable.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's of the nature.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, actually, you should practice impermanence before things change and disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you don't... Well, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You won't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're attached to those things that you find satisfaction in.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you don't see the nature of being subject to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Subject to change while not changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you have something that you're attached to, your family, whatever, your possessions, your view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your views?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: The satisfaction and safety you get on account of you that explains how everything happens, how everything ties in.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is, again, you find safety in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why people withhold such views.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's this leads to that, leads to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why always people want to understand things that happen to them, especially things that cause suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I want to know why it happened.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why did he say such and such thing?
[SPEAKER_00]: Why did she do such and such thing?
[SPEAKER_00]: And having to, like, having some sort of retroactive, kind of in hindsight, extra information feels like, okay, I understood it, I'm fine now.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as the Buddha said, that's a completely wrong way to go about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You get shot by an arrow.
[SPEAKER_00]: Instead of trying to figure out why he shot you, what was his plan, what was his reason, what did I do to him, you put all those questions aside and say, get this arrow out, because I'll die.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, the foolish man does not let the doctor get the arrow out.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, he doesn't do the gradual training, here and now, to get the arrow out, until he has all these answers first met.
[SPEAKER_00]: Why, and how, and what led to this, and how A led to B, and all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you realize, oh yeah, because those views, those information that you collect, provides you a sense of safety.
[SPEAKER_00]: You derive satisfaction from it, to the point that it does actually alleviate suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, somebody said something so hurtful to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Manage.
[SPEAKER_00]: Somebody, something said so hurtful to you, and it's like... you just... you just... you don't know how to deal with that pain, but then you find out that that person was in pain, they lost some... and suddenly you're not in pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, well, you haven't freed yourself from suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just managed it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You just changed its form.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, you remain equally liable to somebody else saying something hurtful.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that means what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Every time you need to find out what's your claim, why you shot me, why you shot somebody else, what did I do to you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Every single time, and you will run out of time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sooner or later, you will run out of time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your view that things are permanent makes you feel good.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't want to think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not an explicit, like, oh, I feel so... but it makes you feel that safety deep down.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's exactly what the sutta says, what it says.
[SPEAKER_00]: Contemplate change.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you stop assuming permanence in things that are dear to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You stop assuming that things won't change.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because no matter how satisfying a thing is...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, say, just keep going on family, say, attachment to family or friend.
[SPEAKER_01]: No matter how satisfying it is, still it's of the nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's on the basis of it is subject to change.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's its nature.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can I...
[SPEAKER_01]: Is that satisfying?
[SPEAKER_01]: That it's going to be taken away at any moment?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, and that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to have your family taken away.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you contemplate, subject to change, in face of things that you don't want to change, you're emotionally invested for them not changing, you contemplate change, you realize your family would still remain there.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to get rid of them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't need to have them arrested or taken away.
[SPEAKER_00]: What will disappear is that layer of satisfaction and kind of comfort that you are finding in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the only thing that would disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: But obviously, for somebody who is not doing that practice, there is the framework of everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything they experience in regard to their family and so on, is first through satisfaction, first through comfort, first through ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why it's scary to contemplate these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because thinking that your family is subject to change will make them disappear this instant, but it will make your satisfaction and safety and everything else built on it, it will make that disappear in an instant.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then what?
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then what am I left with?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Non-satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, then you're left with the actual anicca, yeah, and then you have a choice, as the people in the suttas have the choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay, either I will recognize this and allow it to permeate my being, whereby I will not remain attached to anything that requires my gratuitous assumption of non-changing, because such thing is not possible.
[SPEAKER_00]: Things are subject to change, means eventually they will be taken away.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the whole point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the only reason, the only way someone could suffer in regard to having lost something that they were attached to... Is if they were finding satisfaction and safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: They weren't seeing anicca.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, then, you can ask yourself, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: If, presumably, you know, because you read the suttas, you're familiar with... you have some ideas of anicca in practice.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, ask yourself, like, do your ideas of anicca... do they make you feel anxious?
[SPEAKER_00]: Do they make you feel like there's nothing that you can find satisfaction and safety in?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do you not even feel any of that?
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything just fits... fits into place, just everything is neatly explained, in hindsight, how everything happens, and it's all fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then see.
[SPEAKER_00]: See which one of those is you, basically.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you read the sutta that you just read, you realize which one you should be.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if those views of Anicca were right, you would be free from any... any of satisfaction, any safety in the world, any ownership, if Anicca is fully developed.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, you can ask yourself, like,
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you be free from assumptions, ownership, upādānas, finding satisfaction, finding safety in things?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you be free from all of that without needing to constantly rehash and rehearse the explanations that tell you how everything happens?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when things arise, are you free?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do you have to go through the motions that then free you from things that have arisen?
[SPEAKER_01]: It means you're not free, you're just managing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So there, I find...
[SPEAKER_01]: I find something in my life which I find satisfaction in, that is dear to me, I'm attached to.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you contemplate that that thing is subject to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you feel anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you're attached.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So anxiety is not a problem, as I said so many times.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a symptom.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you contemplate change in things that you deem dear to you, that you don't want to change, and you feel anxiety, that anxiety directly corresponds to the degree of your attachment towards those things, to the degree of your gratuitous assumption of non-change.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize, okay, so, anxiety shows me what I'm doing wrong.
[SPEAKER_00]: I stop having those notions through diligent contemplation of impermanence, anxiety will disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: And the diligent contemplation of impermanence is not you going through the random motions and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's through allowing your thought that this will change, allowing it to endure, not seeking to explain and get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you find things that are dear to you,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you contemplate that they will change.
[SPEAKER_00]: You think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You reflect on that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you have that anxiety.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you leave that enduring.
[SPEAKER_00]: Anxiety, in regard to your thoughts of things that are dear to me, that I assume they will not change, are subject to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: And just leave it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And even if the anxiety disappears, you leave that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only when you get completely distracted, forget, you bring it back up.
[SPEAKER_00]: I needed to qualify that, because people would think then, oh, so then I just have to go through these mental exercises and methods of just repeating mantra to myself that everything... You gotta see anicca, nimitta...
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, exactly, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: You need to... you need to get that sense of, oh, this is subject to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is unownable.
[SPEAKER_00]: Everything that I'm... everything that exists from me, in regard to it, ownership, satisfaction, all of that, all of that,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's contingent upon my assumption of non-change of this thing, but I have no control over it, which means my idea of non-change is ridiculous.
[SPEAKER_00]: This is fully encapsulated in its own nature that is subject to change.
[SPEAKER_00]: And let that endure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Let that thought sit at the back of your mind throughout your day.
[SPEAKER_00]: If things are subject to change, nothing else.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then protect it through virtue and guarding of the sense doors, so you're not distracted and fall back onto finding satisfaction in things gratuitously.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're being enamored with things, delighting in things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That gets removed.
[SPEAKER_00]: That withers away.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, that will wither away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can't find the light in something which is, it's called dangerous to you.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're doing it rightly, through the right view and correct contemplation, withering away of your sort of intoxication with life and things, that will be freeing.
[SPEAKER_00]: The experience of that will not be, oh, I'm depressed now, because there's nothing worth of my satisfaction.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will be, no, I'm free now, because there is nothing worth of me finding safety in it, and thus binding myself to it, and constricting my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if you're honest, you realize, okay, even if nothing's happening now, could I suffer?
[SPEAKER_00]: And what if I don't have the ability or time to explain to myself why and how and
[SPEAKER_01]: All these things happen.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would I suffer?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would I remain suffering?
[SPEAKER_00]: What if I refrain from engaging in retroactive explanations of how my suffering came to be and which is why I'm free now?
[SPEAKER_00]: What if I, just as an experiment, stop doing that part and just let the suffering sit here, when it arises?
[SPEAKER_00]: Would I, would I, would I be touched by it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Will my mind be moved by it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or be completely, completely above it, without any effort needed?
[SPEAKER_00]: But, there is no amount of this explanation that you can kind of install in someone, if they lack that honesty on that personal level of knowing what's happening to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, yeah, simple, again, simple question.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can, as I said, you can quote the commentaries and you can say this and everything is... kalāpas are constantly moving and all this, but that's not how you see things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, is your consciousness constantly moving?
[SPEAKER_00]: Is your life constantly flickering on and off, on and off, on and... Like, that makes no sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if you never heard that external view that you're now kind of trying to fit the suttas with and so on, it would have never crossed your mind to describe your experience like that, because that's not what your experience is.
[SPEAKER_00]: Putting aside the whole thing that if you think you can measure motions of durations of your consciousness in moments and flickering, like what commentaries and the whole kind of contemporary and Burmese vipassana think, that would require you to basically be an observer outside of this experience as a whole.
[SPEAKER_00]: To measure that change.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you can't do that.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't even imagine the outside of the five aggregates, as the Buddha said so many times.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're fully enclosed, so there is no outside point of view for you, in regard to yourself, nor others.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the aggregate of form, feeling, perception, intention and consciousness, fully encapsulated.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, these notions of measuring...
[SPEAKER_00]: I remember, I read that, there was this... the storage of consciousness, the collect...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, how can you even know that?
[SPEAKER_00]: When all you have is your own consciousness of phenomena?
[SPEAKER_00]: But you come across these ideas, these phenomena, and then you ascribe this external value.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, this precedes me, this is the greater consciousness over there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or, or the view, I think, also it was in one of the early commentaries, where, where the moment-to-moment consciousness,
[SPEAKER_00]: Which, again, is just an external idea.
[SPEAKER_00]: These moments last like 0.0 something milliseconds.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's like... How can you measure that?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you measure your own consciousness?
[SPEAKER_00]: How can you measure someone else's flickering moments of consciousness?
[SPEAKER_00]: That's insane.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's fantasy.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: But even if, say, you could see these moment to moment, you cannot see them in that external sense.
[SPEAKER_00]: You are them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your observation of it, your experience as a whole, your intention to look at these moments, remains there enduring for all this time.
[SPEAKER_00]: Your intention to manage your suffering and refuse to allow dukkha to endure, remains there enduring as a basis for all of your other little views that flicker left and right, as you read this or you read that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: The honesty has to bring you back to that recognition of liability to suffer and where your intentions are.
[SPEAKER_00]: And your intentions are not constantly changing.
[SPEAKER_00]: If they were, you would not be able to intend anything, let alone act towards anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: They're the glue, the binding factor that unifies your particular actions that, sure, they're changing, they're fast, because they have a greater context that remains unchanged, which is why you're still doing this,
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why I'm still sitting here, talking, answering questions and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what is the way that one sees things, experiences things, you know, just without going into beliefs and just, you know, from the start you're just here, you're just here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, yeah, I don't... yeah, I mean, like, you... you're gonna have some input.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you just... if you dismiss any information in regard to how you're experiencing things, then you're just gonna mystify it.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's gonna be, I'm just here, and the now-ness, and the is-ness, and the what-if-ness.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, either way, you are not neutral when it comes to experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the question is finding the right information.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the point here.
[SPEAKER_00]: All of this is the information that shows you the contradiction of the other information.
[SPEAKER_00]: The management, how it doesn't add up, how you cannot possibly see yourself in the external sense from which you can measure your own consciousness duration, and all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because of that, you abandon that information.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then you find... but you need information.
[SPEAKER_00]: One of the factors for the right view is the utterance of another, rightly understood.
[SPEAKER_00]: But yes, you have people who say, oh, this information is just causing confusion.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, they dismiss all information.
[SPEAKER_00]: They don't want to read the suttas.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: Part of it resulted in good, because they dismiss all the wrong information, all the commentaries, all the vipassanas, all the modern stuff that's being taught.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then, they also dismiss the right information.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, what they're left with, then, is the complete mystification of whatever's here.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you don't have the means to understand it by yourself.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you did, well, you would be samasambuddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you have... so you have to develop... you have to develop some view.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to develop the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, you have to develop the right view.
[SPEAKER_00]: You already have views.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not a view without any views or standpoints.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you need to develop the right view, the right standpoint, that then, correctly, without perversion, represents your experience.
[SPEAKER_00]: But your experience is always going to be known through views.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why then you realize, with that honest transparency, that if I truly want to be free from suffering then, I need to find the teaching that does not provide another explanation for what's happening to me and another belief and another kind of, oh, this is how it is and that's it, adopt this and you're fine because everything fits.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, I need to find instructions that will make me basically
[SPEAKER_00]: Not be able to experience suffering in the first place.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, if you take that view already... See, that's already like a right view for a patujana, because he already knows where to look.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, that person would then...
[SPEAKER_00]: He would not be too far-fetched to then see how virtue, taming of the senses, solitude... How is that fortifying your mind?
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize, oh, so it's not about just another explanation, just another belief.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about training and undoing this being here, that when touched by feeling, it suffers, it resists, it wants more, and all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's dismantling those reactions, those habits, those, basically, assumptions in regard to that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you say, oh, yeah, how would you start?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, by taming, by constricting the wrong behavior.
[SPEAKER_00]: By taming, by moderating eating, by speech, by all of that.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the mind becomes immovable.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you get to see these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you realize, oh, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: When you understood then, that whatever touches you, whatever is manifested, that's why it's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because it came on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not because you saw it ending, or because this, or you explained it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you realize, I don't need to do anything.
[SPEAKER_00]: For as long as I'm alive,
[SPEAKER_00]: Anything that I experience, I will be reminded of my freedom from it, through that experience.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, this is a sutta from the Dīgha Nikaya, and this is where King Mahāsūdāsanā is passing away, and he's... the Queen visits him on his deathbed.
[SPEAKER_01]: And she says, Sāyā, you have 84,000 cities with the royal capital of Kusavati foremost.
[SPEAKER_01]: Arouse desire for these.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take an interest in life.
[SPEAKER_01]: All these wonderful things that you have.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he's got all...
[SPEAKER_01]: Possessions.
[SPEAKER_01]: All these possessions.
[SPEAKER_01]: Got everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he rules with kindness.
[SPEAKER_01]: And she likewise urged the king to live on by taking an interest in all his possessions as described above.
[SPEAKER_00]: Army, and horses, and palaces, and wives.
[SPEAKER_00]: Jewels and everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Wealth.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when the queen had spoken, the king said to her, for a long time, my queen, you have spoken to me with loving, desirable, pleasant and agreeable words.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, in my final hour, your words are undesirable, unpleasant and disagreeable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then she said to him, then how exactly, your majesty, am I to speak to you?
[SPEAKER_01]: And he says, like this, my queen,
[SPEAKER_01]: Sāyya, we must be parted and separated from all we hold dear and beloved.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't pass away with concerns.
[SPEAKER_01]: Such concern is suffering and it is criticized.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sāyya, you have 84,000 cities with the royal capital of Kusuvati foremost.
[SPEAKER_01]: Give up desire for these.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take no interest in life."
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so on for all of the king's possessions.
[SPEAKER_00]: Before the life ends, we choose to holding on to them.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, there's a suffering there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the king had spoken, the queen,
[SPEAKER_01]: At the end of that sutta, the Buddha goes on to say that famous verse, all determinations, all conditions are impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: All determinations are impermanent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Their nature is to
[SPEAKER_01]: Arise and cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: Having arisen, they will have to cease.
[SPEAKER_01]: They will have to come to an end.
[SPEAKER_01]: Their stilling is true bliss.
[SPEAKER_00]: Their stilling, not their cessation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Their stilling.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stilling of them while they're there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, before things have ceased for that king, i.e.
[SPEAKER_00]: before he died, before things were ripped away,
[SPEAKER_00]: He's advising himself, through the Queen, to abandon desire towards those determinations, towards those possessions, to still them, to let them be, so to speak, to remove his emotional involvement, ownership, satisfaction, safety, and everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if that's not done, there is no...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, the point is, like, okay, so, do you practicing stilling of your ownership, or do you just, sort of, trying to, to, kind of,
[SPEAKER_00]: Inject the view that nothing is permanent, because it would... it would disappear.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's not stealing.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's just another cessation.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you want to steal things before they cease.
[SPEAKER_00]: Stealing of saṅkharas is the peace, is the bliss, is nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not cessation of them, because that's still saṃsāra.
[SPEAKER_00]: They cease here, they rise somewhere else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, again, even that whole sutta rests, the whole notion of anicca, the whole notion of impermanence, on the level of possessions, on the level of things that you desire, that provide satisfaction, that provide zeal, inspiration, will to live.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're still in that desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're not denying the reality and the existence of those things through your secondary hindsight contrived explanations.